I'm William Zaloga,
and I'm going to do a
presentation on the
pathology of restrictive and
miscellaneous
cardiomyopathies. My contact
information is here, and
feel free to contact me.
These are the objectives.
We're going to start
with the general features
of restrictive
cardiomyopathies, and then a
specific one, cardiac
amyloidosis, and generally the
amyloid pathology.
And then a couple more
specific ones,
endomyocardiofibrosis and Loeffler's
endomyocarditis, and
endocardiofibroelastosis.
And the last slide is
good because it compares
the different kinds of
cardiomyopathies that
I talked about in two
lectures on cardiomyopathies,
dilated, hypertrophic,
and restrictive.
So restrictive
cardiomyopathy is a primary
decrease in
ventricular compliance.
It results in impaired
filling of the ventricles
when diastole occurs, so
because the ventricles are
abnormally rigid, not
necessarily thick, but rigid,
systolic function is fine.
There's various types,
with amyloidosis
being the most
common, and idiopathic
mean the exact cause
isn't exactly known,
and categorized in the various
types of diseases based on
what kind of infiltration
they are producing.
So idiopathic restrictive
cardiomyopathy, that's
just a general type of
cardiomyopathy. mouth, the
ventricles are going to
appear normally sized,
maybe slightly enlarged,
but not dilated. However,
on this bisected heart,
this myocardium will feel
firm, depending on where
the amyloid, I mean,
depending on where the
etiologic agent producing the
fibrosis and restriction
and firmness is located.
So these will appear normal
but they can't expand
because they're too
restricted and these pressures
inside will increase and
be transmitted back towards
the left atria, also the
right atria. So because
of that there can be
biatrial dilation and that
can cause symptoms of left
and right heart failure,
but also because these
are dilated arrhythmias.
If you get an endomyocardial
biopsy, it can show
features of a specific
disease in some cases.
Here's the pathophysiology.
A rigid myocardium produces
increased pressures
in diastole and decreases
the filling because it
can't be stretched out,
that produces venous
congestion with all these
signs and symptoms, and
because of decreased cardiac
output, these symptoms.
Presentation are going to be
signs of congestive
heart failure.
Some things you'll see
are increased diastolic
filling pressure,
decreased cardiac output
with fatigue and decreased
exercise tolerance,
systemic congestion, more
prominent, often Often
more prominent in the
lungs than systemic,
often more prominent than
in the lungs is systemic
and these are signs
of systemic congestion
such as JVD, edema,
cites, pedomegaly, rails.
The chest x-ray will show
a normal sized heart or
it will have signs of
with pulmonary congestion.
The ECG will be nonspecific,
and if it involves
the conduction system,
there may be disturbances.
A couple of different types of
disturbances are listed here.
These cardiomyopasies share
nearly identical symptoms
and signs of constrictive
pericarditis. But the
difference with constrictor
pericarditis is that you can
distinguish it because that
can be often correctable.
About amyloid in general.
Amyloid is made of
abnormal proteins
and they build up in tissues.
These proteins are in
the form of fibrils
which are non
-branching and form an
abnormal beta-pleated
protein structure.
The thing about that is
they can't be proteolyzed.
So they're proteolysis
resistant, and they build up
in tissues and damage cells
and leave the cell death.
There are many different types.
Each is due to a specific
protein misfolding.
And they can be caused
by genetic effects
or acquired
environmental factors.
I list a couple different kinds
of categorization of these.
They can be grouped
into localized,
where they primarily
involve one, organs,
and different amyloids
will do that, or systemic.
And sometimes another
classification
is primary and secondary.
Primary, there is no other
disease causing the condition.
It just primarily
affects some disorder
in your physiology
that's producing
the amyloid, you
have normal protein.
That usually affects the heart,
kidneys, liver, and nerves.
Secondary is caused by
another disease like
inflammatory disease, such
as rheumatoid arthritis,
and that commonly
affects these organs.
The four most common
types of systemic amyloid
are the light chain AL type
protein that is released
from multiple myeloma,
those will be the
immunoglobulins, abnormal
immunoglobulins, and
chronic inflammation can
produce AA type amyloids,
dialysis can produce Aβ2M
type of amyloid, and senile,
old age, or what was
another name is hereditary
amyloidosis, produces the
ATTR type of protein, which
is a wild type of
transthyretin that is produced.
The signs and symptoms
and diagnosis are vague,
and you get varied
presentations. Here are
some of the signs
and symptoms that you
can get, but they can be
varied in presentation
and whether they're
present or not.
In AL amyloidosis,
remember, which is the one
from multiple myeloma,
it unusually includes
tongue enlargement and
periorbital discoloration,
purpura, so purple-violet
color, or red-violet
color. In wild type
ATTR, that's the senile
type, it may include the
heart and the tendons.
So a person can have
heart problems and
bilateral carpal tunnel
syndrome or spinal stenosis
or neuropathy or
autonomic dysfunction.
So when you suspect
amyloidosis due to any of
these signs and symptoms
and maybe history,
you can suspect it all
another feature which will
help you suspect that it is
amyloidosis is whether that
protein is found in the
urine so you can find the
light chains from AL
amyloid in the urine organ
enlargement unexplained problems
with multiple peripheral
nerves and it can be
confirmed by tissue biopsy.
Cardiac amyloidosis,
as I just mentioned,
is the major organ
involved in senile
amyloidosis, is
cardiac, the heart.
So there'll be deposits in
the atria and the ventricles.
If these deposits are in
the subendocardium, the
conduction system may
be disturbed, leading to
arrhythmias. There is a
special kind of isolated atrial
amyloidosis, which is more
common in African-Americans
greater than 60 years of
old because of a gene in
the population that produces
a mutant transthyretin.
Grossly, the heart may
show no significant
findings or mildly
enlarged but firm and
typical of a restrictive
cardiomyopathy.
It's rubbery, non
-compliant, and you can see
waxy, subtle nodules in
the atria endocardium.
Under the microscope,
you can see high
-line deposits, which
are amorphous red
-orange areas within
the muscle cells.
And they can be found
in the interstitium, the
conduction tissue, the
endocardium, pericardium,
arteries, the muscles,
and even in the valves.
So it'll look amorphous
and eosinophilic,
sometimes more orange or red.
If you stain that, or
it can seem sort of pale
pink, is another version
that you may see.
And if you see that and
you're suspicious because of
some history and it looks
like it may be a cause,
you can do a Congo red
stain, which will show salmon
pink deposits, but if you
attach a lens that can
produce polarization on
your microscope, then those
deposits will turn into an
apple green birefringence.
So, here's a gross excision
of a wall of the myocardium
that shows amyloidosis as
this pale area. When you
feel it, it'll feel rubbery
and non-compliant, and as
it says here, it looks
paler than the surrounding
tissue and has a waxy
appearance. Under the microscope,
it'll look like these, well,
in this case, pale pink areas.
And you can see that
these muscle cells are
undergoing degeneration
with vacuoles and loss of
the filaments within the
fibers and, you know,
rough, irregular membranes
and loss of nuclei.
So it's producing
necrosis of these fibers.
And here it is under
polarized light
microscopy, apple green
birefringence of those
amyloid deposits
within the myocardium.
Other unusual ones are rare,
but in some places they
can be a bit more common,
but not that common, but this
one here, endomyocardial
fibrosis, also known as tropical
endomyocardial fibrosis,
the clue is tropical, it's
usually a disease of children
and the young adults,
especially in Africa
and the tropics.
So what you see
is fibrosis of the
endocardium and
subendocardium, and it
extends from the
apex to the valves.
The volume and the compliance
of the ventricles is
decreased and there will
be mural thrombi that may
develop due to the non
-compliance and the difficulty
with contraction of that
ventricle to squeeze all that
blood out in the chamber
it's not squeezing an
effective amount of blood
out as well so there will be
possibly you know, some
ischemic changes from this as
well as congestive heart
failure symptoms develop.
It has an unknown etiology
and pathogenesis because
it resembles something
called eosinophilic
cardiomyopathy. So it's
considered to be part of a
single disease, just one
manifestation that includes
Loffler's endocarditis,
also known as eosinophilic
endomyocardial
fibrosis. So Loffler's
endomyocarditis is rare, and it
has endo, but also myocardial
fibrosis, and usually
large neural thrombi.
And, characteristically, you
see increased
blood eosinophils.
And you see
eosinophils in a lot
of organs, including the heart.
These eosinophils
look abnormal, and
they release toxic
products, which
infiltrate the tissue,
produce scarring,
and also produce thrombus.
It's thought to be
associated with the PDGFR
gene abnormality in
myeloproliferative cells
because in those diseases
or disorders, they
can produce hyper
eosinophilia and the gene
abnormalities were found
in those disorders.
It has a poor prognosis
and here's what it looks
like under the microscope.
This is a low power H&E
stain and these small dark
dots may look a little purple
or blue. Those are going
to be lymphocytes and
you can see they're invasive
within the myocardium
and here's a little area
of normal syncytium formed
by the myocardiocytes, but
here, it's pale pink with
irregular edges, so these
are becoming necrotic,
and they've lost their nuclei,
and they have vacuoles,
so this inflammatory
response is damaging these
cardiomyocytes. Here's a
lot of vacuoles, and what
used to be a cardiomyocyte,
there's a lot of vacuoles
here you can see, and these
are becoming vacuolated,
but under higher power,
you can see that these
These are leukocytes which
contain eosinophilic cytoplasm,
that's where all the
eosinophil granules are.
And eosinophils will
have a bilobe nucleus
which will appear
looking like sunglasses.
Another disorder is
endocardial fibroelastosis,
that's uncommon and
has this obscure cause.
It could be the endpoint
of several different
insults, since the cause
is obscure, including
viral infections, or
mutations in a gene called
tephazin, which is a
mitochondrial membrane
protein that affects
the inner membrane.
um people are unsure but
what you get is fibrin
and elastin deposits in
the endocardium which is
thicker and mural and of
the mural left ventricular
endocardium specifically
the left ventricle
it's usually in the first
two years of life and many
of the cases can also have
aortic valve obstruction
here is an excised
heart from a deceased
infant who died
of this disorder
and the cause of death
was cardiac failure heart
failure and the normal
endocardium there's not much
here but this area here
is glistening and tan red
but instead this looks
like a connective tissue
so this is a lot of fibrosis
that's overtaken the
endocardium and is covering
it with a thick layer
so that's formed from
collagen and elastic fibers.
This is a It's a good
diagram because it
compares the three types
of cardiomyopathies
that I talked about in
two lectures, dilated,
hypertrophic, and
restrictive, and gives
various features of
those that are compared,
morphology symptoms,
exam, and pathophys.
So this is a good
diagram to see how they
compare and contrast
from each other quickly.
Thank you, and here's the
link to the lecture feedback.